Hello, we're alive again here and build.
Twenty fifty tradition where the mosque only center and I'm here with anders how are you...doing
...now you do a couple of things for microsoft what is it that you do well
everybody knows that alice...
Well, I've been doing some csharp there for quite a long-time and now I work on type script bunch
...catching fire I mean people are
everybody is using this what was the one announcement that was pretty exciting just a little bit ago about
...tells about that we announced their or well actually google announced the angular team at google
announced they're using...script to implement angular two-point-zero and,
this is sort of the outcome of
...collaboration that we've had with them starting sometime late last year
where we where we made up with the team and then sort of found, you know,
that hey we actually have a lot of overlapping interests here in common ground, you know, and,
why don't we collaborate...anyway, you know,
we might as well do this together and it's been great and we continue to
meet with them often and work on problems in the angular types group space,
... angular is a substantial framework to test types group
gone has the what kind of success of a ad with well,
I think I mean for them day-to-day sort of have come to realize that you write a
large code base that there's a lot of value in having static types in there because you can
check to go before runs as opposed to while it's running and,
I think for them also for documentation purposes types make a lot of sense because
ultimately when you're writing a framework you end up with tons of entry points and things
I've neat documentation and you need to write
it down somehow in a consistent manner and using static types and
in a type system makes just times...so for those that are new to
type script what is it the...is doing how does how does a process go from writing types
...actually generating javascript what is it all about what so types
...is a statically typed or optional you typed superset of javascript
...that compiles to playing javascript icy so it allows us
to have during development time allows you to happen static types in your javascript program and
those static types can guide intelligent tooling so you can get wonderful
features like statement completion and find all references go-to definition and refactoring that are
What they want you compile all the types evaporate and you're just left with
plane javascript that's number one thing it does the other thing it does
is it's a download leveling transpire?
Icy meaning that you can use.
we as we say features from the future today you can use ecma
...six features and down level compile them to
ecma script five or ecma script three javascript...run in any browser because even though
...script sixes close to ratification as a standard it's going
to be years and years before browsers actually before you can
assume in your apps the...the target browser supports ecma script six I
mean even today you can't really assume...script five even though
ignore script five is almost like five-years-old now right so would you say that types script
...the type trip the languages a bridge to what's coming in the future is type trip
going to be not necessary when the next version of...because this is just a cycle repeats right
then we're already now implementing some features for microscope seven or proposed features for
...group semis...a single weight like decorator...for example,
and, that cycled world, you know, as
long as javascript keeps evolving you'll have the same cycle.
...school so I went on to get...and,
because typhoons...get hub and I see here design goals
...I the reason I like this is because once you're clear about what
type trip is versus what it is...it's really easy to make decisions about
what kind of features that you're that you have so I just there was one I
had a question about let's take a look at this so produce a language that
is composer bullet easy to reason about easy for the programmer easy for the trance pilot
what is
...goldie...well did it's like motherhood and apple pie right I mean guy
who doesn't want that I do think...that easy to reason about means
you know, ideally there's not more than one way of doing a particular,
particular thing right I mean some languages over time end up with a lot of
craft them tons of different ways of doing stuff compose of all I think.
One of the at least to me what that means or has meant is,
you know,...ability to use the language nod just as a traditional
command line compiler but the ability to imbedded in tool sets
...a variety of different place and you see that now that we have id logins for
god knows how many different id right like well of course visual studio and
...new visual studio code but also web storm sublime text
adam like eclipse I mean you did that the list goes on,
you know, wrap-up of great plugins they give you all of
these advantages that I talked about early like statement completion and refactoring so forth
what's cool we have some questions coming at a christian says now...type script supports the
...modules is the old module syntax being deprecated that's an excellent
question it's not well, it depends on what you mean by deprecated we will continue to
support and we vote and it's not going to go away but,
we will definitely encourage people to use the new ecma script six?
Standard for modules right and then I think everyone is going to want to do that
but we're not we are very conscious of not breaking code god
...so backwards compatibility is king now we are doing some
renaming...we used to have two kinds of modules and we still do
or things that we called modules we have we called internal modules or name space
modules or, you know, sort of the ability to create an object rooted in a global name space with
objects inside it and then a dotted paths into it and then we
had what we called external modules which is common
gsm amd modules or renaming that terminology recalling the old internal modules we're going to
...namespaces okay and the new modules that we used call external moderates we're just going to call
a...because that's what...six calls them
...from here on out module in types grid means and ecma
...six module got a name space means
...space kind of internal modules that...revealed
...but both will continue to be supported we are adding
...just added last week a new
...space keyword that you can use instead of the module keyword just because it just
makes things make more sense but it's all optional again it feels like type script has a
set of features that you can either opt interrupt you could write...javascript
...ripped and everything's okay sure I mean if you do that then types
...really functions as a later right it just tries to infer
...that can and they can only go so far without type annotations but
it's still will point out a bunch of stuff right but then as you add types you can sort
of gradually dial-up the hell, you know, and, you can even...up to a point
where you say I would like you to verify that everything has a
...type in this program okay because and we even have it's called the knowing
...at any compiler...once you turn that on you have an assurance
that refactoring are safe because nothing
has a unknown type and therefore we know what everything belongs to and therefore you can
...safety and I think there's
our that especially when you're building something that's really large.
Yeah, I'd say the larger,
larger it is the more applicable types...skylight and, you know,
as you get into really large teams and mit many people
working on it it's just an invaluable development and got it so another,
another question how secures type script code
...try for panel functions like eve out which often causes some problems and javascript, yeah,
well, types...doesn't handle...in any particular because types
...is a development tool not at run-time to got it so we don't make any
guarantees about what's going to happen at runtime it is up to you or the runtime environment and
...to use the...what we do is we give safe types to
everything so we reduce sort of the chances of that right and wrong right but we but we
can't as a as a compiler.
Ensure that you don't do this because you have any you can do anything you can and javascript
all right so ...can you do algebraic data types with types reputed
...recursive data types that's an interesting also eighties are kind of
...of types that are found in functional programming languages and you pretty much can
we have union types in types group
we certainly have recursive data types or types that depend on themselves and their
own definition absolutely we are looking at doing.
Some language extensions that would allow us to do matching also
over types that have unknown qualifier or discriminatory matching
it kinda like pattern matching although it's more it it's not going to look exactly the same
...on our website...actually on the get
...there's a couple proposals for some of that stuff so you can find it up there, yeah,
that's cool okay next question any
plans support types script even some type something like bar, yeah.
...the question a little bit as we all know...good question,
yeah, the question is are we going to support types like...this type is both a
and b I...like where you mix together to types out and,
some types indeed...would be useful for...where,
you know, you sort of mix in some members from another type and it's something that
we're thinking of you can sort of do...today with inheritance I mean because that in a sense
...sometime...your but, it's not a type operator and,
...look we're looking at doing that we have intersection types now are union types okay but,
we don't have we don't have some types,
yeah, all right so fill...the ts...a types...compiler support double quotes for
...templates additionally to back...because back...on...
probably not I mean because we already have.
Javascript already has to find.
Back take to be the one that you use for template strings and,
if we were to add another one I think it would add more confusion...may it may solve the problem but then it's
going to create another problem right and adapt point it's not clear to me that it's worth the tradeoff, yeah,
so, let's talk about some of the new stuff because it looks like your argued hub
what's the process for your desired you have
the design notes online could people contribute to that yes and,
yes, they can...and, we basically, you know, the sort of
life-cycle of a feature typically starts with an issue or suggestion I
...all called issues on get hot but it's tag suggestion typically someone
will write-up a suggestion and we do that even for the features that we implement but,
of course the community will suggest off and then a discussion will
ensue and then we will triage the suggestions in the type
script development team and then we'll either tagged like okay we're going to accept
...request on this one if someone wants to do it all we're going to commit to do it there, you know,
depending we basically treat all features our own
versus community the same way it's the same process and that's all it's all indeo open yeah,
what are some of the new things coming out here that people can look forward to...while so?
Right now we're on a fast-track to finish...six
...we don't we just today announced types...one-point-five beta which?
Takes us from while type hard-won five takes us from implementing a few ecma
script six features to only lacking a
...more script six-feet guys we pretty much jumped and
...we now cover the broad majority of features but
there's still some like generators or nadin yet that we need to that we need to finish off and,
that's what we're going to look at doing in types
good one six we're also looking at spiking some ecma
script seven features versus we've already implemented decorator so we're looking at a
...awake we have an experimental branch that...
Going to virginI
think in one six and then we're looking at module bundling and then finishing off ecma
script six though that's sort of like that's going to keep us busy for probably the remainder of
the next six months...got it got it
okay so another question you have any plans to improve workflows and packaging of types
...javascript code as part of it type script project ideas
...feature I met
I mentioned here module bundling is something that we will likely...
to the compiler itself the ability to inside a project use ecma
script six modules for all your code.
But, then bundle it together and produce a single output file out of that where all those
modules are sort of bound together so they can still have external dependencies and things
can have dependencies on them that's a feature that we lacked today and,
for that reason if you're using modules in a browser you
need a module loader or module package or like js pm or
require js in order to load and run your modules
...so, for sure that's something but in general I think we also have the.
What I have to the point of view that we want to play weld
...can't do everything, yeah, so, it's going to always be important for us to just be able to
plug into pipelines of javascript tooling and, for example,
if you don't like the way we're going to bundle modules well you can always use types group to produce ecma
script six output and then use another transpire to do your bundling and,
people do different they put it together in different ways and...committed to?
Fitting into the into the process well-put also picking sort of
an eighty ninety percent case that we want plum all the way through...
make efficient because.
As you...as you snap...get along tool chains.
Something's got to...hours resource lower right I mean so,
if you care about performance that is not always ideal so, pisces always
...all right so another question from
blogged are you going to spend any time improving the developer experience...working with things like harmon
...tests and types...today is a little difficult that is comma testing framework I'd I believe so,
yeah, I think.
Yeah, I mean we're always looking at the to willing I think.
For the last year so we have been very heads down on just we gotta get a
...because that's what the community...for a lot of these things
ip we do work-up bunch with the community on these on these things so,
for example, build tools we have great supporting
...grunt and gulp and, you know, we have great support in a variety of id...and,
you know, unit testing I think is another area where we could perhaps, you know,
take more input from the community you got it so looks like some people are asking some csharp
questions so let's talk a little about csharp what are some of the new things
and csharp coming out now and tell us a little bit about csharp for the future how do you
envision it so...what we're coming up with now and then future
...so csharp six is just, you know,
about to...ride in visual studiotwenty fifteen and,
csharp...a fairly light-weight.
Release language...that there are a bunch of smaller features in
there like the like...operated the question...operator,
for example, is one that comes to mind right but, they're sort of
...of csharp
...last product cycle has been finishing roslyn and moving on to that new compiler
...right which is what we have...and,
literally and in...twenty fifteen we have a brand-new compiler, you know,
it's a different it's a new brand-new code base
brando id with a lot of cool new features and, much better extensibility and,
it's all opensource...that's a tremendously difficult undertaking
and it's a big out it's, you know, it's writing...compilers hard writing a compiler
for language that is a decade old and has millions of uses where you've got
to be backwards compatible with every little bit because it might
...is that the old compiler was quirky with some...there
...they work their work works and then now you sort of what do I do too I implement the
...do I implemented...but then I will break something right so all of these things you
gotta like consider that's crazy so what about what about the future of csharp
we're just we're starting
...csharp seven ...process?
Right now actually are like in the last couple of months and,
we're looking at things like novel types is a big one and there's a whole,
you know, we have actually it's...on get up, you know,
I would urge all the go look and,...the dialogue about what what's, what's how often are you
looking at those things that people are submitted...while the team looks at the daily
I don't look at of daily but, I participate in the
design group for csharp dot so I
...every...anything that makes it into the language I will definitely have been involved in the discussion
...so let's get some more questions christian when building...there always is some code
insight html files will there be tooling refactoring to support types script code
Yeah, we.
I probably.
I'm not sure I would recommend putting
...statically type code in the middle of an html page I
probably urge some refactoring there, you know, where you where you end up with the code
...a code file...the html and html five most of the modern frameworks
work that way anyway and I encourage you to work that
...so I don't think we will see sort of
a resurgence of type scripts imbedded in html would you see
that's maybe a smell for this needs to be changed a little bit well,
it's justI think generally speaking you're going to do better when the to were separate because
otherwise the only thing that can work on your code is the thing that implements the
...that you union up the to...you can find a ton of html tools and,
you can find a whole bunch of types...tools and id that support types group but you're going
to find very few that supported both right so, you're better
you generally better off keeping these assets separate hiding now here's another question this
is interesting from tempted microsoft have to re implement the roslyn compiler for linux
...sex I think is going to...some of how this thing works...
we did not because the
rousing compilers written csharp what we did have to re employment or well it's not
a completely implementation but we have to implement a dot net clr on
...x and linux and ads what the dot net core project is about moving?
The code base that previously was windows only...always sects and,
linux and audit once we once we have that I'm were very close dan roslyn
we'll just work I mean it already works with mono...riled so you can already
run our compiler on those environment but
it's but, what this actually gives us the same code base
for all of the os so there's a difference between the run-time and what the
compiler is producing right so those are separate things well, yeah, I mean and in dot net it's like the
compilers just innocence and application bright-eyed I mean that
so happens to produce applicant augment applications, yeah,
all right so here's another question I love the csharp six features
surfing what potential ideas on the table...we...yap, yeah,...so,
which brings me to another question that similar that there
is this interesting intersection now between folks really dig in the functional
stuff and then there's the imperative stuff that we do and csharp...yes and they're starting to
come together yes where would you draw the line?
They're alive.
No,... we're sort approving over time that there isn't really a line right I
mean no functional programming language is purely immutable
because you've got a produce some output at some point it's a question of how immutable you are
right and functional languages tend to favor commute ability heavily where
...languages tend to favor stateful imperative and,
we're sort...all exploring the intersection
between thoseI will say in the projects I've worked on, you know, recently or,
you know, like roslyn and type script it's a lot of the techniques we use
inside compiler, for example, are actually functional programming techniques and
alive immutable data structures just because there's?
Especially in this world of computing that we have now where you have you have you
have mutable state and you have multi-threadedand,
you can have one or you can have the other but never ever do both rotates
...because that is a recipe for...right.
I mean if you want...ability you gotta be really,
really careful about just having threads run around and, that and modify your state but if
you're immutable and you can share with zero cost.
Right because all you have this guy references never changing,
you know, so, great you can have as many threads
as you want reading the seeing data right and that's always safe
got it and sometimes you just...like...that dad is.
As a programmer a very liberating way to think about the problem because it
is by definition safe you don't even have to worry about right and,
that's why I find immutable...very attractive as a
programming to serenity csharp moved more...readability and
...definitely looking at of course we are we can't we can't completely deny
our heritage...we are at the core
and object-oriented imperative programming language right but,
certainly in...the last many brute releases we have added features that
of all been very inspired by functional programming languages and, dabbled
clearly continue and immutable the is one that we would love to formalize somehow right,
yeah, well, the saying goes if you have a
problem use threads now you have to problem that's what I was
...abraham lincoln said that on the internet I thought...was, you know,...
There's another question how active
...you on csharp and types ripped which takes most of your time and
...kind of like a good these days I spend most of my time on
type script just because I ended up actually implementing a bunch of the compiler and,
then so that's what I get my hands dirty
...my coding right now but in the design space I'd say
it's fifty I mean I participate in the csharp...in the typed design...how much of the
employer...csharp influence type script or was it like it's just we need to start again
of about javascript and then make javascript...
if everything you do influences what you do from there on out right I mean and,
pascal influenced csharp influence
...the...ted I diagramming into the
...up so yes it did it did you got
it all right any plan to add csharp like extension methods to types
...that's it, yeah,
probably not I mean...thing about.
That the thing about javascript is that you can already in a
...hackett you can you can walk up to any object start adding methods
onto and...even those even like, you know,
a technique called poly filling that we use to emulate
...script six in ecma script five environment by adding all of the
missing methods to all of the system classes and than an
...right so the problem that csharp solves with
extension methods is already in a sense solved it's just solved in a different manner
...in javascript and we do indeed have the ability
in types script to extend existing type by writing to declarations
ford let's say someone has written some type is some interface type you can go
right and interface type with the same name and the to automatically merge
...at compiled us cool...so,
we do have something that similar it's just done differently so I
don't know if people know this but the new visual studio code what
...types group have one and, I know I was...I know the and measuring there's no data
so-so visual studio code is written in types gripped it's basically.
The...it runs in is...it's called the electron shell one
and it's a window hosting environment that was produced by the adam team
...adam the creates the...io editor and,
the tvs code team uses that same shell but...has implemented a different
editor and html web-based editor the and they've implemented it all in
types group and it's I forget how many lights go resolve are way over a hundred-thousand lines
...all written in
...at the cool thing is that it was hiding under our nose under the code they monaco that's right
it was an internal project called monaco it's actually been public ever since day one with
typed because the playground for types group uses demonic co-editor and
monaco all of the all of
...completion and language support that was in that little edit...a since has
grown-up and popped out of the browser and we're not out of our...and
over-simplification...because there's a whole lot more stuff in visual studio
code but I think the thing that I like about that project is that the team
that has worked on it for these for these past several years has been dog food
...along so does the tool that they have use themselves for
years and that's why this varied this first release comes out looking so polished,
you know, because this isn't...all that new,
you know, it's been around for a while so we have about half a minute left what information do
you want developers today to know about types...go to get started what advice do you
have while to get started go-to type scribbling dot org and that'll pretty much
link you everywhere I would say if you're if you're interested in the language
are interested participating please come to our get help repo...and,
get involved, you know, I mean this is opensource and,
we've got a very active community there and we'd love for anyone else to
join I like it because...you say get involved...me get involved by writing type
tribune get...writing about...to know...writing
...but get involved in writing...to with you if you like...thanks so much for spending some time
mobilization thanks for much for thanks so much for watching and we'll catch you after the break take care.